I'll begin with a roll call and seating of alternates.
I see,
let's see now who's present, Jed Larson.
Yep, here.
Jim Hallisey?
Here.
>> And I don't see
Commissioner Smith
on the call.
I do see alternate William Monroe
So I'm going to see alternate William Monroe in place of Commissioner Smith.
Okay. Again, the agenda for this hearing is consideration
of IWWC
application
twenty-twenty
seven,
Rubio Negen Puerto
at 129
Hebron Road,
the application to
erect concrete
stone wall and fence,
inground pool, utility shed,
and two car garage with accessory apartment
within the upper review area.
We should note, of course, that the application
that was considered in our previous hearing
has been subsequently
substantially
modified.
However,
in order to affect the completion of the hearing,
I will ask first if there are any comments
by any of the commissioners.
Again, any comments or questions?
Okay.
>> Yes. I my name is Jim Halsey, and I have
questions for the chair.
I I'm just looking for a clarification as to
what the application includes insofar as the septic system,
what approvals are in place.
>> Maybe agent Wagner could speak to that. All I know is what's posted on the website.
Yeah.
>> This is agent Wagner.
The septic system is
on this application. So it needs to be considered as part of this application.
Oh, and it's
it's on the plan, the new site plan that was submitted.
Thank you.
>> Okay.
Any other questions or comments from commissioners?
Okay.
Okay,
seeing no further comments
or
questions about the
application
regard to the hearing,
I will entertain a motion
to adjourn the hearing
so that we can proceed for our regular meeting.
Jim Halsey, move to adjourn the public hearing.
Mr. Halsey has
moved. I need a second.
Don't be shy.
I'll second.
>> Okay, second
by
Commissioner Larson. I'll
ask for a vote on the motion. I have to do it, of course, by roll call.
Commissioner
Halsey.
>> Chairman Elliott,
could we have
I have a question before we proceed to the vote.
>> Wait a minute. You want to back up and talk about the application
is this for the hearing?
Yes.
Only I question say that.
>> My only question is were we going to solicit input from the public during this public hearing? Oh, I just heard you ask the commissioners. I'm sorry. No, then subsequently asked if there was any further public input
>> and didn't see any hands raised or
comment
to that effect.
So as I say, let's proceed now. We have a motion on the floor seconded to adjourn the hearing.
Again, by roll call, Mr. Hallisey has already
voted to.
Commissioner Larson?
Aye.
Commissioner Monroe?
>> And I, Vice
Chairman Elliott,
vote aye as well. So the motion carries four-zero.
We will now move to the regular meeting,
which commences immediately
following the public hearing at 07:06.
The
roll call and seating of alternates will be as for the hearing.
And the next item on the agenda
is the additions and changes in order
to the agenda.
I have been advised
of at least a couple of
additions.
And I would first propose that we add
to
Section eight, Permit Applications,
IWWC
twenty-twenty
seven,
the application that we just considered in the hearing. We have to have it on the agenda for the meeting
in order to consider whether not it should be approved.
That's
I will, as Chair, make that motion to add that item to the agenda.
And I'll ask for a second. I'll second.
Yes, we have a motion
and a second.
That was from
Commissioner Larson
to
add
IWWC
application 2,027
to the agenda
as there would be item 8A.
And of course, subsequent
applications
would be re
designated accordingly.
And I'll now call for a vote on the application on the motion again
by roll call.
Commissioner Hallisey?
Aye.
Commissioner Larson? Aye.
Commissioner Monroe?
Aye.
And Mr. Elliott also votes aye.
So the motion to
add to the agenda
carries.
In addition,
we have received,
subsequent to the printing of the agenda,
but in time for inclusion on tonight's agenda,
a new item,
which I'm trying to dig up here.
Okay, an application
for
construction
at 26 Old Farms Road. That would be
item number 7B
on the agenda.
Could I have a motion to add that, please?
>> Larson makes a motion to add that to the agenda.
Ballasty,
second.
>> Okay, so we have a motion and a second to add.
I believe WC 2,036
in the agenda.
I'll call for a vote again by roll call. Commissioner Hallisey?
Aye.
Commissioner Larson? Aye. Commissioner Monroe?
And Vice Chairman Elliott also votes aye. So the motion carries four-zero-zero.
And finally,
we received
a request
to consider
modification
of a permit previously
issued
for
construction
at 344
Lake Road.
I'm going to propose that that be added to the agenda
as
item number 6B,
because it seems to be essentially a jurisdictional
request
regarding,
again, the conditions
for modification
of a permit
that has already been issued.
This just came to my attention this afternoon
from
agent Magna.
About ten minutes.
>> So
again, I'll need to ask for a motion
to add that agenda item.
>> Allicy, move to add
request for modification at 354
Lake Road to the agenda. Do
I have a second?
I'll second that.
>> Thank you.
Commissioner
Monroe, I believe. Okay, I'll ask for a vote again by roll call.
Commissioner Hallisey?
Aye.
>> Commissioner Larson?
Commissioner Monroe?
And
I
vote for Elliot. Also vote aye. So the motion carries four-zero-zero.
Are there any other
requests
for
additions
or
changes
in order to the agenda?
Okay, hearing none,
I will move to
agenda item number four, approvals of minutes.
First, the
minutes for the regular meeting of 11/02/2020.
Again, I'll ask for a motion to approve
so that we can discuss.
>> Larson makes a motion to approve the minutes from November two, twenty Second.
>> Okay.
Any commissioners have any
comments or
questions about those minutes?
I have just a couple of
really minor items.
On page five,
under the
consideration
of the
request
for
jurisdiction ruling at the Andorra Sports News Club for timber harvest,
There's a sense that these
harvest of dying emerald ash borer,
which should be harvest of ash trees dying of emerald ash borer.
Don't we wish that the emerald ash borer were, in fact, dying?
Okay. And
in that same paragraph, there's a sentence, the project is cut to length,
which
doesn't make sense to me. It may be forestry's talk.
And if anybody has any suggestions on that one, I'd be happy to entertain them.
Okay.
Well, I guess we'll just have to read where it stands.
So any other revisions
to
the minutes
for that meeting?
Okay. I'll ask for a vote on the motion to
approve the minutes as
with revisions as noted.
Commissioner Halsey?
Aye.
Commissioner Larson?
Commissioner Monroe?
And
I,
Vice Chair Elliott, also vote aye. So the motion to approve the minutes carries four-zero-zero.
Then we have the minutes of the 11/14/2020
special meeting.
And again, I'll call for a motion to
approve.
>> Larson makes a motion to approve the
special meeting minutes from Saturday, 11/14/2020.
Second, Allisie.
>> Any
comments?
Need for revision?
Okay. I'll ask for a vote then to approve the minutes as received.
Once again, Commissioner Hallisey?
In favor.
Commissioner Larson?
Aye.
Commissioner Monroe?
>> And I, Vice Chair Elliott, also vote aye.
So the motion carries four-zero-zero.
The minutes are approved.
Item number five,
public comment. This is the time for public to comment on the items
that are on the agenda for tonight's meeting.
You should probably
try to
raise your hand or
text or comment to
our board clerk, Mindy, because I may not
see
if somebody does want to make a comment.
I take it there are no public comments.
We will then proceed to
item number 6A
of new business, a jurisdictional
review
for IWWC
twenty-thirty
four JR
Joseph Thoreau,
who's present at the meeting,
on behalf of Ronald and Joan Cherny. You see Ronald Cherny is also here.
We're the property owners at 110 Cone Road
who wish to harvest timber
on
a
site property they own,
which involves activities in a watercourse and associated
upland review agents
or upland review area. Remember,
this is a jurisdictional
matter right at the moment. We don't have an application.
Essentially,
question is whether this activity
requires a permit.
I'm
going to ask
Agent Wagner
to speak to this issue because I believe he has
some
discussion
and
familiarity
with the inquiry.
>> Yeah.
I don't I don't have too much. I didn't visit the site.
I talked to
Joe Thoreau.
He went out and took some pictures of the wetlands crossing sites and the picture of the material
that they're using to make the temporary bridges.
Put them together and they're posted on the town website. Hopefully
everybody got a chance to view them.
Yeah. Nothing's been started yet.
As far as I know, last time I talked, they were unloading stuff there, but I think
mister Thoreau would be able to provide a better description.
>> Okay. So this is this is Joseph Thoreau.
Right.
Yes.
Crystal Christopher Leveque is the logger that's gonna be doing the work there.
He has deposited both of his pieces of equipment on the property,
but that has not really gotten going yet.
To facilitate removal of timber,
we have two two wetland crossings in the town of Andover.
If you look at the cutting plan, the first one is labeled WC1,
and the second one is labeled SC3.
WC1
or Wetland Crossing 1 is a very, very narrow here.
Jimmy, can you bring those up as a share?
>> Is it on the submitting and pending approval?
This map?
>> Mr. Thoreau is that the
map that you were
referring to
>> I'm
not virtual.
I'm just here on the phone, so I It can't see what's going does appear. It's a map that shows the property at Cone Road.
Yeah, I think we can see that.
Yep.
Okay. So you said So if
>> you look right at the town line, there's Wetland Crossing Number 1.
That's gonna be
used to to access the
the western portion of the property.
Several of those portable bridges that you see, the photos of will be laid out there
at the completion of the operations.
The logger picks them back up and,
you know, seeds and and mulches mulches the crossing sites.
Crossing SC 3
is a narrow
intermittent stream crossing. It's a very rocky site.
Same thing. He's gonna be using the same portable bridges.
Very, very small amount of timber is actually coming out of that that small
upland island, if you will.
And that'll probably be towards the end of the end of the job. The same thing at the at the end of the at
the end of the operation, he'll remove those bridges and, you know, back blade or grade grade the skid trails on either side,
the seed and mulch the the crossing sites.
As far as the timber harvest is concerned, this is a a management cut.
We're just simply
we're taking out about maybe a quarter to a third of the volume of the timber.
Again, just to really remove over mature, poorly formed disease, and
oaks that were in decline.
I'd say the time frame of the operation probably run more or less
three weeks to a month, provided he has good ground conditions. We don't get too much rain.
If during,
you know, the operation,
if ground conditions
tend to get muddy, then he's a very he's a good operator. He shuts down,
waits till the ground conditions to improve.
That's basically it, but I can entertain any questions you may have.
>> Okay. The the the big question here is there there don't seem to be any existing
crossings. These would be new crossings.
Correct?
>> Years ago, this this timber was cut,
and there are most of it actually where you see those those skid trails or main haul roads is labeled,
There were old trails there. Yes. Yep. So I'm actually using
existing crossing sites.
>> Crossing sites.
Okay.
Yep.
Okay, any other commissioners have any
questions or comments?
>> This is Commissioner Larson. I had a question
from the pictures.
I did not understand why we would be seeding and mulching following
the crossing when it doesn't look like there's any vegetation in the area at this point.
>> Well, what happens is when the machine goes over those bridges,
there is there is minimal disturbance there. And of course, the the skid trails on either side of that crossing site
are bare mineral soil. So it's always important to put in water bars
and seed and mulch on either side of the crossing site because what that does is it stabilizes the
it stabilizes the
the soils. So in the spring, when, you know, when when everything greens up, it's it's it's definitely a better a better way to do it. You don't just not not seed and mulch.
The hay that and just put simply putting the hay down also helps to
stop it when it rains, you know, that you don't get as much disturbance.
This is a common common practice on on stream crossings and and wetland crossing sites
>> do we have any other
questions or comments from
commissioners?
Okay, well,
I guess we have sufficient understanding at present.
Again, the question here is whether
Inland and Water Crisis Commission has jurisdiction
and has whether
a permit
will be required.
And for the purpose of
proceeding with the discussion,
I would like a motion to the effect
that a permit
is required
for this activity.
>> Larson makes a motion that a permit is required for the logging activity?
Well,
>> the wetlands crossing activity, if you would. For the wetlands crossing to support the logging activity.
Thank you. Alex Segal second that.
Okay,
comments,
discussion of the motion.
>> Mr. Chairman, can I speak or no?
This is Joseph Thoreau.
>> Yeah, this is
a discussion for the commission with respect to the
requirement for a permit,
not the activity itself per se.
We've
got recently Are
>> you going to allow me to speak or no? Well,
>> Okay. Is your comment germane to the question of whether or not you need a permit? It is actually.
>> It's
germane to the fact whether this is a permitted use as of right or whether it's a in fact a regulated activity.
Okay
Then I'll I'll entertain
your comment.
>> I'm a I'm a wetlands agent for six different towns in Eastern Connecticut.
And in I I I have yet to have
any commission rule
that
the temporary stream crossings used
for forestry operations
are
regulated activities.
If you look at at section four of your regulations,
if you look under the definition of agriculture,
forestry, and silviculture,
they are specifically
permitted uses as of right
by definition.
>> Right. That's correct. We have
heard that assertion previously.
And
I will call the attention and ask
the commissioners to recall
the
legal advice we obtained
from our attorney, Mark Brantz,
that
case law suggests that deposition
of material in the wetland and watercourse
is not permitted as a right,
even though it is in support of an activity
that may be permitted as a right.
>> So Mr. Chairman,
how do consider
the placement of a portable bridge
that's being removed
deposition. I I I feel deposition of material
means,
pipes,
culvert pipes, fill materials,
filter fabric, things that are meant to stay
in place permanently.
These are just some simply structures like log corduroy.
They're placed to simply
protect the wetlands, and they're taken out afterwards.
>> I understand that.
And again,
I'm only relaying the advice of our attorney to the effect that
No, your attorney. In a previous
discussion,
where, again, our previous jurisdictional
ruling,
we were exactly
that question.
Again, it was a consideration of an
proposal to use temporary
crossings,
such as the ones that are
proposed for this
activity.
And again, we were advised
that,
according to case law, that would be considered
a deposition.
And frankly, I don't want to get involved in the
adjudication
of that question.
I'm simply
relaying that to our commission
as a point of departure for this discussion.
>> Commissioner Hallisey,
recall
that evening in a marks attorney Francis
recommendation
was calling
basically, he included temporary
fill.
That's saying,
I
I mean, I'm sure,
tracks of land are logged all the time as a use of right without
permits.
I
agree with
Chairman
Elliott in that. That was certainly Attorney Branch's call. That was his recommendation there.
I have to say he's wrong.
Complete idiot.
>> Okay.
Commissioner Larson, do you have
comments
or recollection on that
advice?
>> I
recall the advice
just as you had stated it,
Chairman Elliott, and when we were discussing
the Andover Sportsman Club, that was the
difference between that and the previous application where we went
the other way. So
think your recollection
is exactly what we were provided by our legal counsel.
>> Yeah, the Andover Sportsman Club
issue there were already
crossings in place.
So there was no new activity
to regulate.
In this case, we seem to have and that's why I asked about whether these crossings
were existing crossings
or whether as they appear from the photographs,
they appear to be de novo
crossings
that would, again, involve
even temporary deposition
of material
in the well for the purpose of facilitating the crossing.
And
I appreciate that this is good practice as forestry
and that
there are
reasonable differences of opinion and interpretation
on
this activity. But I think that given the fact that
we have been advised by counsel and have previously ruled
that
this
specific sort of activity
should require a permit,
think that we're pretty much obliged to
continue
to request a permit in this
situation.
And one other comment, if I may.
Commissioner
Larson?
>> I'd like to go on record saying I think our attorney is not an idiot.
Would you repeat that for me? I'm sorry. Disagree
>> with the comment that our attorney must be an idiot.
Thank you.
Okay. Any other
comments from commissioners?
Can you hear me?
May I speak? I'm Ron Cherny, the land owner.
Yeah,
I suppose so.
>> Thank You may have spoke. Should be. Yeah. I think two things. One is
that the
land was clogged not too long ago in 1988
after Hurricane
Gloria
and Jo Nichols from
the town in Boag there she was the state forester in charge of that operation there
and like
Joe Thoreau had said I think that we're using some of the same existing crossings there so I don't see how this is anything
any much different than what it was done just a while ago and also I'd like to
have
Joe Wagner make a few comments on this whole thing, if we could. It has to go
through this permit process.
>> Well, again, that's the question here.
The commission has to determine
whether or not a permit is required.
>> Okay.
And what saying
is not
too long ago in my lifetime, it was
pretty much the same as what's happening at this point in time. I don't know if anything has changed that
makes makes it much different than what was just done.
That's
basically my comment.
I don't know if Joe has been believe up with that plan if he has any further comments on this.
Can you repeat the question?
Who's
who's speaking?
>> This is Joe. I I I
was just asked a question or
No.
No. Joe Joe Wagner.
He he's
>> he's the wetlands guy from Andover.
So I just was curious on his comments. How is this any different that was just done in recent time
about thirty years ago?
I don't believe any permit was required at that point in time.
>> Yes.
Agent Wagner here. I'm not
sure that was well before my time.
The
comment that I have for the commission is,
just,
like, if a is there more information that is needed for the wetlands crossing to make the decision? Like, I I'm just like, practical looking at the practicality of applying for a permit, like, if it's gonna be
just the same information as this notification
but in permit form,
it just seems like
it would be
would be unnecessary because it's not you're not asking for anything new.
Whereas if you needed more information
to make a decision about the wetlands processing,
that might be different.
>> I'll
respond to that, again, Vice Chair Elliott.
The
fact is that
a permit
requires an application.
Right now,
we are being asked for a jurisdictional
ruling,
which is a different matter.
If we were to decide that
we don't have
jurisdiction,
then that would obviate the need for a permit.
But
if we do decide that we have jurisdiction and permit
is required, yes, the permit will
incorporate much of the same information.
And we will be making a decision
on we will make a decision on the permit
on the basis of the same information.
But in fact,
much of the information that
is being presented
in this jurisdictional request isn't
about the jurisdiction.
It's about the proposal.
And again, this is a very narrow ruling that we're making.
And the fact that we're asking for a permit simply means apply for a permit.
And
I can't
again, speaking a little ahead of ourselves,
I can't see any reason why we would deny that permit because it seems to be a perfectly sensible forestry plan.
The question is, again, based on precedent
and
for
this commission
and based on advice of
our legal counsel,
I believe that we
do have jurisdiction
that
that specific aspect, the wetland crossing aspect,
is
under our jurisdiction
and that a permit will therefore be required.
And again, I don't think that
I don't want any further public comment
on that question.
This is a question for the commissioners
to decide,
again, based on our
understanding
of requirements.
>> All right. This is Halsey. And I
appreciate the
applicant's
input here. I also
do remember what attorney Branson said as
a commission.
I think we should follow his advice. Curious if as an alternative,
this is jurisdictional ruling,
whether the commission has,
whether the commission,
their permit is required. Is there an alternative? I mean, this
would,
if there was an app, if there was a permit,
an application in place, is something the agent could handle
on his own.
I apologize if I I I just don't really understand that process
about as very well if you have to make things go
to me.
We haven't had a
agent
authorized.
>> No. This is well, this is the activity in the wetland, so it would have to go through the commit.
All right, so that is not an alternative,
>> you're saying? Right. If a permit is issued, we could definitely hand it off to Agent Wagner. I mean, if an application is filed, if a permit is filed, permit application is filed,
we could definitely hand it off to agent Wagner for determination.
>> Well, the agent can only approve
activity in the upland review area. So and if this was the activity in the stream processing
>> and you think it needs a permit, then it would have to go back before the commission.
I see. Thank you.
>> Okay.
Any other commission
comments,
questions?
I would like to proceed then to a vote on the motion. The motion, again,
is
to the fact that
the commission
that the Andover Inland Wetlands and Water Courses
Commission
has jurisdiction
and that a permit will be required
for the wetland crossing and upland
and activities in the upland review area.
Mindy, is that a fair statement of the
motion?
Yes.
>> Okay.
Without And further discussion, we'll go to a vote.
Commissioner Halsey?
Can we go over the motion one more time?
>> Okay. The motion is the fact that the commission has jurisdiction Jurisdiction, yes. And a permit will be required.
Aye.
Okay. Commissioner Larson?
Commissioner Monroe?
Aye.
>> And I, Vice Chair Elliott,
vote aye. The motion carries four-zero-zero.
Again, we'd be happy to entertain an application
for a permit for the forestry activities,
which could be submitted for our next meeting in January.
Okay, moving on.
We added agenda item 6b,
inquiry
regarding
a previously approved
activity at 344
Lake Road Construction
And Clearing.
Let's see. This just came in today.
And
Agent Weiner, could you
introduce this? Because I think you've
had a lot better handle on the correspondence
than I. I saw the copies and
looked through it. But I believe let's see,
is engineer
Hanfield
on this call? I am, yes. Okay.
You're 860798.
Hopefully I'm on the
there you are. There we go. Okay.
>> Joe, do you want to introduce it or do you want me to make a run?
>> I'd like agent Wagner to just briefly introduce it and then hand it over to you.
At
>> engineer Hanfield, I'm sure knows much more. It was a while ago we talked. But
>> yeah. Basically, I guess the permit was previously approved by this commission a couple years ago,
and
no action was taken with it. And the new owners wanna basically do a similar thing.
So
engineer Hanfield is wondering if he could if we could modify or use the existing permit.
that's what I know.
>> Okay.
Mister Hanfield, could you
briefly explain?
I don't know if
let's see now.
Mindy, can you bring up for screen share
the
proposal,
the site plan?
I
don't know if it's posted online
or whether it an email
or what.
>> It was an email. I'm not sure if it's going to be there.
>> Oh, if it's an email, I probably don't have it.
Oh, Okay.
>> You allow
us to share a screen?
You've got a screen to share,
Mindy, can you let him
>> Yeah, hold on one second.
All right, you should be able to now. Okay, I'm going give it a shot.
>> Hey. Can everybody see my screen?
Yep. Okay. Great.
So this is the are the minutes from April
1738.
And just wanted to basically
show that it was approved unanimously.
Presentation.
>> Right here. Approve the proposal.
Sorry. Too far.
Here we go. Approve the application at 344 Lake Road.
And this is the plan that was presented to you that evening.
So what you see
in orange is the existing house.
And
in between, the the front end of the proposing and the disconnect to.
And in addition to that, they were proposing
a large septic system
to the east.
They were going to basically take out the existing town drainage pipe and realign it in the road.
And there was a significant
area of clearing here to do all of that work. So this is the limited clearing.
This is a reference of what was approved.
What I submitted today was basically
the preliminary plan of what the new owner wants to do. And what I did is I overlaid the original limit of clearing
and seal prints to give an idea of the original disturbance limit, which is in magenta here.
And then I also overlayed the proposed house in orange with the original footprint, which is also in magenta.
It's a dash line again connecting the two. So
you see that the new addition is smaller. It doesn't connect the two structures anymore.
But it's within the original
footprint
of what was being proposed.
In addition, there's no longer a proposal to put in a septic system or move the town drainage pipe
and all of the grading associated with it. So basically,
we're going to propose to use the same temporary construction road that was proposed originally.
We're going to scale back
tilt fence and clearing limit line to only
cover that temporary access drive
and build a smaller addition within the same footprint
that actually
it results in a substantial reduction in the disturbance of the upper review area from what was approved.
But again, it's within that same
footprint and is generally the same project or scope of project minus the septic system. So
what this proposal allows us to do is use the existing septic system and that's why the house would step back like that.
So
I can field any questions, but we're we're hopeful that
we can get confirmation that this is in line with the original
permit approval, and then we can pull the building from it based on that from it to improve.
>> Okay. Yeah. So the essential question here for the commission is
whether or not this
requires
a
permit revision application.
And
the salient factors are, first of all, a new owner,
and
secondly,
the
downsizing
essentially
of project parameters,
both in terms of the
structural
and the
site modification.
Believe,
Agent Wagner, I believe you were advised
that
the provision in our
regulation and
our conditions for
permit
regarding non transferability
is probably non enforceable.
Yeah,
that's
what I was told.
>> So
let's just
drop that one from consideration
and
raise the question then of,
again,
is this activity
a
revision
that would constitute
requirement
for
reapplication?
I'll ask for
comments from the commissioners.
Mr. Halsey?
>> Yeah, this is Halsey.
I'd like to know what the conditions
the original approval were,
particularly the duration.
I know they
typically run between two and five years.
And the conditions that I've read said you cannot
renew an expired permit.
I believe this one was actually a five year permit. This was a five year. Okay, then that's not an issue. Thank
>> you.
Although nobody seems to be able to
Mr. Hanifield, have you been able to find
the actual notification
>> on that? It seems to have gone into the other zone. I went as far in just for full disclosure, the previous owners were my in laws.
And I went as far as asking my mother-in-law if she had a copy. And
she's pretty diligent about her paperwork and does not. So
I'm not aware of anyone has a copy of the actual
letter of approval.
All I have for the minutes in my conversation with Mr. Valenti, but that's all
I have. Okay.
>> And I believe Agent Wagner also made some effort to
in the town files.
I couldn't
find it there.
>> Okay.
So
again, absent
that, we will
take it as read that it was a five year
permit. That's what we understand.
>> Vice Chairman, Elliot, what was the address that we're talking about here? I think I got confused with
the Shea application
when we were talking No, this
>> is a 344.
And again, it's an old application.
It was approved in 2018.
So we don't have anything. There's nothing posted on that. It's all
been simply email
and
phone
correspondence
to
initiate this
inquiry.
Okay.
Well, seeing no further
comment or questions,
I like a motion
to the effect that
well, again,
based on our previous
procedures,
we should make a motion that
a
permit
modification
an application for permit modification is required?
If we don't think so, we can vote no.
So could I have that motion?
>> This is Larson. I'll make a motion that a permit
modification
is required to 344 Lake Road.
I'll second. Second?
>> Hollis. Okay,
again, as a point of discussion here,
frankly, don't think that this does require
affirmative modification. I think that
since it's a
reduction
in
the scope of the project and
really no other essential changes in the project that would impact
wetlands,
I think that
the owners should be
free to go ahead
with
the plan
as revised.
Further
modifications
might require
application.
But what we've seen
tonight,
and what was presented by engineer Hanfield,
seems to be
perfectly acceptable and should not require
an additional
application.
Anybody want to argue that point?
>> This is Larson. And I guess my concern is that if nobody has a
copy
of the permit,
why we wouldn't expect to start
it over so we do have a paperwork
document to go back on when we're doing something.
I don't know how we can proceed without having a copy of the permit to modify.
>> I take your point. We do have proof that the application
was approved.
>> Yeah. I think this is agent Wagner. And according to the regulations,
the the
minutes count
as a permit.
I'm trying
I'm not sure what part of it is, but I remember reading that.
>> Yeah, mean,
have the original application,
right?
And again, we have the minutes of the meeting where they were approved.
The
documentation
that's missing
is
essentially the notification.
Do we have the application?
I haven't seen that.
>> Again, I think that that was
was the application,
Joe, among the
documents that were
circulated
by email?
Yeah, I think they were.
I can double check.
>> Is that something that was circulated to all the commissioners? Because I got the afternoon email from Joe talking about
the Shea application, but it didn't mention anything about this.
>> Okay. I received that in an email. I
don't know how well
Faradkai distributed, to tell you the truth. They came in this afternoon.
>> I would prefer
to defer the
decision until the next meeting where we have a chance to at least review the information that we're talking about.
>> Yeah. There's a copy on
in that
list of emails. Megan Lawley had a copy of the application.
I can send it to
Mindy. If you have it, you can share your screen if you have it right now.
I
enabled it so everybody
has permission.
Okay. Where do I do that?
>> So if you move your cursor, it says share screen and it's in a green button in the bottom middle. And then the pop up windows and you just select whatever window
that's in it.
See that?
Yep.
Yeah. This is the application.
>> So essentially what we're looking at is the
conditions of the application.
And
again,
the
proposal here is simply to do
somewhat less
than what was originally requested.
Since that activity
was
permitted,
I don't
see any need to revisit
that
application.
>> I understand what you're saying, Vice Chairman Elliott.
I just fundamentally
opposed
to something coming before the commission that we've had no heads up on.
And it comes here
during the meeting where you don't have time to review it and to make a jurisdictional decision on it. I think that is the wrong way for us to be doing business.
>> That's
a valid point. And I would
entertain, first of all, a withdrawal
of the motion
and a
subsequent motion to defer further consideration
until our next meeting.
>> If I may say one thing.
Mr. Hennfield. Thank you. I apologize. I didn't mean to spring this on anyone and create
confusion.
We were actually trying to do
as the development of the plan came along, I tried to get it in Friday, and it was on me that you're not open Friday, so I missed the deadline.
But what we're trying to do is make sure we're doing the right thing
by
basically
showing you the plan and being upfront with that information that
we are moving forward with the project.
It is a similar project, but it is significantly less in scale.
And we don't want to go forward with that whole project. But we wanted your blessing.
So I understand the last minute notice and
would be understanding either way,
but with full discretion. We really wanted to make sure you could see the difference in the plan and how much less we are proposing and
be comfortable that we
would hopefully fall under that original permit because
we do believe we could construct the original permit
and and the activities that were proposed on it, but we don't want to. We wanna scale it back.
And
but we'll we'll we'll go either way. And and, again, I apologize for the last minute.
>> Returning to the question at hand, we do have a motion on the floor. And we'd have to withdraw that
motion
and the second there, too,
in order to defer action.
So who made the motion?
The motion did.
Okay.
You want to withdraw that motion?
I would like to withdraw that motion. Okay.
>> Mr. Halsey, I believe you seconded I will withdraw my second, yes. Okay. So
back to the question.
Mr. Larson, I think the motion
here to
defer further consideration to our next meeting would be in order.
>> I'll make a motion to defer consideration
on the application for 344
Lake Road to our January
meeting?
It's actually jurisdictional
rule.
It possible
to see the two plans?
You want to see the plans again? I'm sorry.
Not today.
>> Yeah, think we get those posted on the website
and get
all that stuff taken care of.
>> Yeah.
Saying if we could see both the
approved plan and what's
>> currently proposed. And
by the way, I did like the overlay that you did showing the
difference.
I'll make sure you have both documents.
Okay. Thank you.
>> So back to the side, we've got a motion
to
defer further consideration.
Can I have a second?
I'll second that.
>> Thank you.
Let's go to a vote on the motion.
Commissioner Halsey?
Aye.
Commissioner Larson?
Commissioner Monroe?
Aye.
>> And aye. Vice Chair Elliott vote aye. So the motion carries four-zero-zero.
We'll take up the 344 Lake Road at our next meeting. Thank you. Okay.
Next,
we have
new applications.
First,
IWWC
thirty-thirty
five
for
activity construction at 436
Lake Road.
Again, because this application
is received
effective this meeting,
we will not be able
to
act
on the application
until our next meeting.
But at this point, we can certainly entertain
questions or comments
from
commissioners
regarding
the
application and the
supporting materials
that were posted.
If folks had a chance to
look at this application.
I have two
questions.
First to Commissioner
Larson,
Chair of PZC.
Wouldn't this make a great test case for the proposed lake regulations?
It would.
>> Secondly, for all commissioners,
should we schedule a site walk?
Larson thinks we should.
>> I think we should.
Saturdays at 09:00 seem to our
go to time for
site walks.
This Saturday is supposed to be in the low 50s with a
small chance of rain.
But that's about as good a condition as you can ask for at this time of year.
>> Like to make a motion that we schedule a sidewalk for this Saturday at 09:00.
Policy would second that.
>> Okay. I'll ask for a vote on that motion.
Policy?
Aye.
>> Larson?
Monroe?
Aye.
And Elliott, aye. So
sidewalk,
09:00.
We'll get an agenda up. And we may have an addition to that
on our next point.
>> Is Jeremy Elliott Yes. We have any other discussion on this application tonight?
>> Sure we can. I had asked for it earlier and didn't see anybody's hand raised.
>> Go ahead. So on the application in paragraph nine for the proposed erosion and sediment control and other management practices,
it does talk about
minimizing pollution or other environmental damage,
maintaining and enhancing the environmental quality.
So I think those words and under it it says see the attached sheet and I did not see
an attached sheet that talked about
mitigation factors that might be put into place to
minimize the effect of the runoff into the lake that would be
going on due to the proposed development.
So I wondered if I was missing something.
>> Very
good question.
We might address
that.
Okay.
Does the applicant or engineer on this call? Think
yes, I see.
I
think
fingers with us.
>> I
I think the attached sheets was the drawings,
the
site plan,
which shows sedimentation and erosion controls that has said fence
down gradient of all this
this disturbance.
Sorry. I I don't have the technology to show you the drawings, so you you have to have the drawings in front of you.
But I believe that's what what it was. I'm
filling in for Jim Dutton. Jim Dutton had a ZBA meeting
in another town, and
he did the actual detail of the site plan. I've reviewed it.
I'm
his engineer of record.
>> I did look at site plan and what I was hoping
is the intent of
our
zoning regulations
for the lake
and
it's to encourage property owners who are developing along the lake to
provide at the time of construction significant mitigation to minimize stormwater runoff
into the lake to prevent
with the weed growth and algae growth and all that sort of thing.
And so I was looking for maybe
some measures like
running the
gutters from the house into a dry well or
something like that to mitigate the runoff from the driveway
something.
And I didn't see any of that on the site plan.
>> Well, the driveway.
The driveway drains towards the road.
And,
and the gutters in the front of the house or on the road
side of the house, I guess it would be the
east
portion of that. All those gutters are directed
to drain away from the the lake. Eventually, it'll end up in the lake.
But this
way, it has
much longer run.
There's a grass swale along the driveway.
So those were some
of the things that are proposed.
There's a let out proppants
in the area. So dry wells,
I'm sure we could find one if if if that was insisted upon. But there was some thought taken
to to
direct the runoff away as much runoff as possible away from the lake.
>> Okay.
And that's the kind of thing that we are looking for. As you say, the runoff, even if it goes towards the road, will end up in the lake eventually.
And so
we are trying to minimize
all of that to
maintain the
quality of the lake. And I'm sure that the new property owners or the potential property owners
have a vested interest in making sure that our lake stays healthy
going forward.
And when they're building the property, that's the time to put these measures in in the most cost effective manner. So I would ask for their consideration of looking at that.
>> Correct. And Jim Dutton, he'll be at the
sidewalk
Saturday
with plans.
He can expound on some of the details.
The
plan is very detailed.
>> If I can add to that, it's not just
avoiding
and mitigating well, but act with measures
to
enhance
the property and its ability
to absorb runoff. So
active
certainly
minimizing the impact is the first step,
but then
measures
to
enhance
quality
as an offset
for that construction
activity.
Okay.
>> And again, I think
Commissioner Larson
has the greatest current
familiarity
with the proposed
regulations
and can
probably offer some guidance
on
trying to achieve those goals.
But for now, we'll again look forward to seeing you at the sidewalk
at 09:00.
And
again, we'll take up this application
at our next regular meeting.
Okay.
Thank you. Any
>> further
questions or comments
on
and on 3035?
Oh, one thing. I noticed that some of the PDF files
associated
with this application online
were actually mislabeled
and referred to 2030 Three-ninety 7 Lakeside Drive.
I expect it was just an accidental
cut and paste
in renaming
>> files but yes was that on the plans or it
>> was it was on the plans as they were posted
you know the final things that were posted online But that's probably
whoever I don't know who actually
uploaded those to the town website.
Oh, Okay.
It's a common It
>> wasn't your number.
It wasn't the engineer's numbering. It's very common
for somebody to miss
cut and paste.
Okay,
>> moving on.
We have another new
application.
This is
IWWC
2000And36
for Number 26
Old Farms Road.
Again, that's
an application that we received
in time for the meeting, but not in time to be included
on the
agenda,
which is why we added it.
This is an application
that was
stemmed from we previously discussed
the proposed work.
It was brought to the
commission
previous meeting as a sort of hypothetical.
And we now have the actual
application.
Again, since it's a
new application, we won't be able to take action,
but I will
ask for questions
and comments
from commissioners
if you've had a chance to
review the application at this time.
>> Yeah, this is I have a question
through the board,
whether they feel it's significant activity
that would require public.
>> That's a good question in two parts.
First of all,
is it a significant activity?
There's
probably good grounds for saying yes.
However, I've
re evaluated. I looked closely at the regulations,
and the regulations state that
we shall hold a public hearing only if
we determine it to be a significant activity.
The regulations do not state that we must
have a hearing if it's a significant activity.
In other words, being a significant
activity or significant impact
is a necessary but not a sufficient condition
for a hearer.
My
previous understanding
again, this was based on oral communication
from our former wetlands agent
was to the effect that if it was a significant activity, we have to have a hearing.
I
now question that interpretation
of the regulations based on my reading.
Got that?
>> I do. Okay.
I was just trying to avoid
setting a public hearing later in the process.
>> If Yeah. I agree. We can have a hearing, it to would be
determine it now
rather than That's my point. Later.
So other comments?
Mr. Larson,
any
>> I just reached over to get my regs because I was under the same misconception
as you were that if it was a significant activity,
it would require a public hearing. I'm just getting
the book out so I can
lay my eyes on the words
as well.
So I'll defer for a moment.
>> You know, on the other hand,
is a sidewalk is going to be
set.
Commission may
feel more comfortable making that determination after such time as you've
seen the site.
>> Part of well taken, and I certainly
have on my notes for this item that we should schedule a site walk.
Would it be agreeable to continue the special meeting site walk from 04:36
Lake Road and go across town to Old Farm Road.
>> If you're looking for a motion, I'd be happy to make one. Is that okay? Yeah.
But
>> we'll set
up a sidewalk for
'26 the 26 Old Farm Road application
to immediately follow
Lake Road
sidewalk on Saturday.
Okay,
motion
It'll be circa 09:30.
Larson will second.
>> So we have the motion for a sidewalk.
I'll call for a vote. Came by roll call.
Commissioner Hallisey?
Aye.
Commissioner Larson?
Commissioner Monroe?
Aye.
>> And Vice Chair Elliott also votes aye. So the motion carries four-zero-zero.
We'll have a sidewalk
following
Saturday
following the sidewalk
on Lake Row.
So that will be our agenda for that special meeting.
Okay, returning to the question about
whether or not it's a significant activity.
>> Mrs. Larson, I would like to make a motion that
the proposed activity is a significant activity.
I'll
ask for a second on that.
I'll second it.
>> Okay.
We have a motion and a second to the effect that this is a significant activity as defined
by regulation.
Any
comment or discussion on that motion?
Commissioner Larson, you could speak to the basis for that.
>> Well, the
different conditions
for significant
activity,
does any activity involving disposition or removal of material which will or may have a major substantial
effect or significant impact on regulated area.
I have not seen the property, but I am under the impression that the
proposed driveways in fairly
steep
section of the property and would require a significant amount of fill.
And that's why I think that it might be a significant activity.
>> It does involve
fill and in fact construction
of
concrete
retaining walls
for that fill
over a culvert
in the stream,
a culvert to carry the water in that stream.
And
if you look at the site plan,
you'll see that they're using interlocking concrete block
to hold the fill.
So I'm inclined to agree with you that it is a significant activity,
significant impact
on that watercourse.
Any other
discussion or comments?
>> I do have a comment going back to the
proposed sidewalk.
Yeah. I think we should clarify where folks
should meet.
>> Yes,
indeed. Good point well taken.
Do we have a suggestion from the engineer or owner
as to an appropriate location
to begin the sidewalk?
I I would think that the entrance
to the driveway or the proposed entrance to the driveway would be reasonable.
Yeah. So I think
go ahead, George.
>> Yeah. We can meet at the turnaround
at the cul de sac of Pine Ridge.
Jim, does that answer your
Yes, it does. Okay.
>> Okay. I'm looking at
just lost it.
Section
I'm sorry, I lost my place in the document
regarding
Okay, Section nine, public hearings.
Section 9.1
says,
the Commission shall not hold a public hearing on an application
unless the Commission determines
that the proposed activity
may have a significant impact on wetlands or water courses,
comma, a petition signed by at least 25 persons who are 18 years of age or older and who reside in the municipality
in which the regulated activity is proposed,
so forth. So
we may issue a permit without a public hearing,
provided no petition provided for in this section is filed with the commission.
So
again, based on my
reading of Section 9.1,
the determination that it's a significant activity
does not entail
a hearing.
It authorizes. It allow us to hold a hearing. It would justify a hearing, but it doesn't require it.
Larson, I
agree with
what you had just said.
>> Good.
Glad to have a court here. So returning
then to the motion
regarding significant
activity.
We have the motion and second. We've had discussion. Any further discussion?
I'll call a vote
on the motion.
By roll call,
Commissioner Hallisey?
Aye.
Commissioner Larson?
Commissioner Monroe?
Aye.
And
Vice Chair Elliott?
Aye.
So the motion carries four-zero-zero.
We have ruled that it is a significant activity.
And we have scheduled a sidewalk
for,
let's say, it'll be about 09:30, 09:45 before we get there.
And
I suppose that if we have some means of notifying you, we could do so immediately as we leave the prior site, I give you a heads up.
>> We can pass a phone number on to
maybe Joe
to get that distributed.
Yeah. Yeah. We can do that.
K.
>> Okay. That'll work. Great.
Okay. So I think that we can now move on
to the agenda. Pardon? Chairman would
Yeah. I just like
>> suggest that you maybe
have the applicants give a quick presentation of
their application. We'll
>> have the we really can't consider the application
until
the next meeting.
And
it's
something that's come before the
mission previously,
at least in a conceptual manner.
And we've got a rather lengthy agenda here.
So, I'd rather
move on. Again, we'll have the sidewalk.
We've got the
plans,
the detailed
site plans.
And I think
we'd be better off to defer
further consideration of this until our next regular meeting,
when we'll actually be able to take action
on the application.
Unless any of the commissioners
wish to hear more
about the application at this time.
Okay.
Thanks to the applicants
for your
attention. And again,
I would like to move on,
because we still have
several
items
to consider.
In particular,
item 8A,
which has been on our plate for quite some time now,
outpatient
visit 2027
for activities
at 129
Hebron Road.
As previously noted, during the conclusion of the hearing, we have a significantly
revised plan.
Would the applicants
or their agent
like to
summarize and present
those revisions?
Can you hear me right now?
I can
>> who am I Can you hear Russ Heinz,
applicant
agent?
This is 860798?
Yes, 7986160.
Okay. You're not identified on screen here.
>> Is your name again?
Russell Heinz.
I'm
a
principal with Tarbella Heinz,
the preparer
plans.
All right. Thank you.
Okay.
>> So I
just quickly,
I didn't think we could talk after a public hearing was closed.
We are now
in the meeting.
>> Okay. I realize that. But I thought I was supposed to present my stuff at the public hearing, but I will present it now. So
I was told by
Joe,
New York Wetland agent,
and you are as the commission that you are not
happy with the location of the pool,
of the shed, of the
garage and we moved it
as much as I could to meet the health code
and
to stay away from
the wetlands as far as I could and
keep what my client wants to have and
which is what you have in front of me. And I did try to make it a little more clear to you how we what was existing and what was proposed.
And I believe the shaded
is the proposed and
everything else is existing.
And
we are far as
plan revised
eleven-twenty
five-twenty.
>> Exactly.
And
as far as the septic system,
that was approved back in,
I want to say,
by the health department.
I've not really changed that.
And
the only reason that's not been built yet
is because according to the health code,
until that system fails
or until they add any additional
as in
the garage,
which has got the apartment, if they hook that up, if they need to add something to that system,
then that has to be put in. But until now, as of right now, that septic system does not have to be installed.
So that's kind of where why
the
way it is at this point.
But the addition is all been done. The house has been built,
and they're just really
wanna put their wall up.
>> As I look at the plan,
the
fence
now stops
at
mark about 100
feet
Basically at your regulator. Outside of the regulator, correct? Yep. Terminates outside The the
pool and
the
garage apartment
have both been moved closer to the existing structure,
so further away
from wells. From the wetlands.
>> Right. Okay. Then
I would like to ask commissioners
if they have any questions or comments
regarding the revised application.
Commissioner Halsey,
you had
questions regarding
the original application of these
revisions. I don't. Have no.
Okay. So,
these revisions essentially satisfied your
original
questions?
Yes.
>> Okay.
Commissioner Larson, do you have any
questions or comments regarding revisions?
>> I just had a question on septic
design going to the leach field.
Am I reading the drawing correct that we're pumping that uphill? It's not flowing downhill, we're pumping uphill.
That's
correct.
Yeah, that was the only question I had.
>> Commissioner Monroe, did you have any questions about the
proposal?
>> It looks like the
wall is going to stop right
along that 100 foot
upland review area?
Yeah.
>> That's what I was told by my client
to do, or I was told by that's what you wanted, and that's my client agreed to that, and that's where it'll stop.
K.
I'm happy with that.
>> So let me just
make sure that the commissioners are ready to
act on this application.
Obviously, we've
been
on it
quite some time now, and we've seen some extensive revision
of the
plan in relation to concerns that we raised.
Again, I'll simply point out for the record, these were not things that we specifically
requested,
but asked to be addressed
based on the input we received
from reviewing engineer
and from public comment on
the previous
hearing.
So
as far as I'm concerned, I would be ready to entertain a motion
to approve the application
with standard conditions
as it is
currently revised.
>> Chairman Elliot, I was
wondering if we could get the agent to
address if there were any additional
conditions of approval that he would recommend to us for this application.
Certainly.
Mr. Wagner?
>> I
can't think of anything specific that I would want to add.
>> Currently,
we're looking only at activities in the Upland Review Area.
And
with
a portion of the building
and the pool
both being within the Upland Review Area, at least in
almost majority
of those
construction activities would be in the Upland Review Area. We've really taken all of the wetlands
impact
off the table at this point.
>> Mrs. Larson, I'll make a motion to approve the application
subject to standard conditions of approval.
Do I have a second for that motion?
I'll second that.
>> Thank you. So
we have a motion and a second to approve the
application as modified
with standard conditions,
application IWWC
twenty-twenty
seven, 129 Hebron Road.
Any further discussion
on the motion
on the application?
I'll call for a vote by roll call. Agent Commissioner Hallisey.
Aye.
>> Commissioner Larson.
Commissioner Monroe.
Aye.
And
Vice Chair Elliott also votes aye. The motion carries four-zero-zero.
Agent Wagner,
we'll
pass the ball to you to
issue
the
that will be in two weeks because, of course, we still have to allow for public
comment
on
the
application.
Okay? Okay.
>> There you go.
So
moving on with the agenda,
the next item
is application number twenty-thirty
for the
bridge activity
on Cider Mill. We haven't received any
further
information
on
the
application
per se.
However, there has been
some
communication
with
our attorney
and with the applicants
regarding that.
Agent Wagner, could you bring the commission up to speed
on
with a summary of what's transpired
with respect to this application?
>> Nothing really. I haven't gotten anything new.
We did the sidewalk on the fourteenth.
That was that
was it. I I
don't have any new I didn't have any requests from the commission
to seek any more information from it, and we didn't receive any. So
>> Right, well, of course, as of the sidewalk,
we were just gathering information.
And I think now is the time for the commission to
speak up on
the application and its
adequacy
or inadequacy
as the case may be.
I do have some comments, but I'll
wait for other commissioners to
put an order in first.
>> I
have a question.
Yeah.
Is this a temporary bridge, or is this gonna be permanent?
>> According to my reading of the
my understanding of the application,
they intend for this bridge to be a permanent structure.
>> I just asked that because I've seen that, Brooke.
I'm sure you have go crazy.
When it floods.
>> Exactly.
You've
raised a very good point there.
Essentially,
it seems to me that the application
is
far from complete.
We just don't have enough information
about
the construction of the bridge
or its
potential environmental impact.
We saw
on the sidewalk
approximately where it's gonna go,
but there was no delineation of the exact landings on
either the east or west side of the brook.
We were told that it would be
land on the west side of the brook
such that it would avoid the steepest part of the grade
on the Western Bank.
And on the Eastern
Bank, it would land on what appears to me to be floodplain
that would be
northerly of the existing
drive way pad.
Everybody
had that same
impression,
but there was really no plan for the bridge.
We had a sort of a generic
bridge design.
And we had
a
general location
and a general
assertation
that there would be no excavation for footings
to support the center of the bridge, which would be two spans
meeting in the middle.
But
as I said, we just really don't have much of a plan there. And
questions such as Commissioner Monroe just raised about flooding events. So we've seen Staddle Brook
in full roar.
And I
can't imagine that a bridge
at that
level
wouldn't
obstruct
flow and catch debris,
and so on and so forth.
So it would have to have
impact
on the water course.
But we can't evaluate.
Anybody else wanna weigh in on this?
>> This is Halsey. I I do have concerns.
Obviously, bridge
that would require an approach
on either side, which
you have to assume require
fill and grading.
I understand too the applicants was just
some
feedback whether they proceed far into this. I
do appreciate that.
That's what concerns with what happens on the other side with any vehicles. That's a fairly steep
hill.
I say vehicles.
My understanding would be,
only intended right now for equipment for repair,
But nonetheless, it's a bridge that's
going in there in perpetuity for all
intents and purposes.
Yeah, I have a big concern about, also the I'm curious as to whether,
would trigger a stream encroachment.
I
don't know the I
don't know when that when a stream encroachment
permit required it.
Just came to mind that you weren't required it.
>> Point well taken,
And
I certainly couldn't address that question myself.
Again, as we say, it does seem that
it's quite likely
to
interfere with the water course,
maybe not under
normal conditions,
but under anticipated
high water conditions,
it almost certainly
would
interfere with flow.
There's also the question of
whether any alternatives
exist.
I'm gonna
have to switch over here. Excuse me. I'm gonna pull up that
application.
Minnie, could you put that application on the screen
for sharing?
So 20 dash
30.
Yep. Thank
you.
>> What part would you like me to scroll to? Scroll down to
>> well,
essentially, we're looking at
number nine,
which calls for alternatives considered inseplicately
rejected
by the applicant
and why the alternative set forth on the application was chosen.
All such alternatives shall be diagrammed on-site plan or drawn. Well, we don't have a proper site plan.
We've got a sketch.
But we don't have any consideration of alternatives.
And again, my understanding
here
is that there may be a possibility
of accessing the property,
by an easement
from an adjoining property.
Now, that would be complicated,
but that's not our concern.
So again, what we have is
a generic
drawing
for a
short span timber bridge
and
an approximate location
on the map.
But we don't really have a site plan
showing
any of the topographic
features.
None of the detail that I think would be required
for evaluation.
With that in mind,
I would propose that we defer further consideration
of this application
pending
receipt of further information
from the applicants.
I certainly don't think we could accept
this Yeah,
Commissioner Allsey?
>> I'm just curious if the applicant is available, and maybe
we could give them
some more direction.
>> Right, yeah, we do need to give them direction on that.
And I don't know if the
applicant or
agent
on the call?
Doesn't look like it.
>> Perhaps agent Wagner and I could work together to
summarize
the
aspects of the application that
wouldn't require attention.
>> Yeah, I could come up with a list and send it to them, work with them to try and get a more detailed plan for next month.
>> Yeah.
Again,
the real key is the site plan, the impacts,
and
potential alternatives.
Again, as in the
email
correspondence
that you had with Attorney Branch.
>> Vice Chairman Elliott, did you say there was some information from Attorney Branch with respect to this application?
>> It
was
not on the application per se. It was more an advisory
regarding such applications
and
especially the question of the
alternatives.
We can certainly
forward that
information
to
the commission.
I don't know if it should be part of the record
for the application or not. I want to take that under advisement.
But
I I I certainly think that it could be shared with the commission.
I
>> would also recommend that one of the alternatives
that they might consider is
making the bridge where they proposed it a temporary bridge.
They're moving the equipment in and out during dry season,
that's totally different than having a bridge there year round with
the significant
>> rushing through the brook. Right. So, yeah, that would be a good question to raise. Would a temporary bridge,
a temporary span
suffice
for the purpose.
The only downside I could see there, Jerry, was to be that if they wanted then subsequently
to
do some more work, they have to reapply for a permit for another temporary crossing.
But yeah, that would
certainly having a temporary crossing in the dry season would obviate
a lot of our concern.
>> The reality is it's not a timber bridge. It appears to be a
designed
lumber. It's an engineered lumber bridge, really. Yeah, exactly. I mean, says timber on one, on the little picture,
cross section,
it's engineered lumber. And it's significant
projects.
Yeah, it's a bridge.
A lot of expense for it, don't worry.
>> Not quite on the same scale as the covered bridge downstream,
but still.
No.
>> Okay, so anything else on this?
We don't have any motions or anything on it, so I think we can move on
if we're ready.
And again, the understanding is that we'll communicate
our concerns
and
requirements
to the applicants
to be addressed at our next meeting.
Okay,
application number 203285
Lakeside Drive.
We've had one new
well, we've got additional information on that,
namely
we received
notification
of approval
by the Andover Lake Management
Association.
So
it's good to go from that point of view.
Okay,
I see
Mr. Miner is patiently online
as a representative
for the owner.
And
I'll ask, let's see, any
questions or comments from commissioners
on this application?
>> This is Larson, and I had a question concerning
the transporting
of the rock for the rock wall down to the lake.
And I guess my question is in the form of a surprise as I walk around the lake at 422
Lake Road
where all of a sudden I see a temporary road installed that leads down to the lake.
And I know that's a very reputable
contractor that's putting that wall in over there. It was just certainly
not expected by me when we discussed the application. So I was wondering what
kind of precautions or whatever you were taking to protect
the ground or
whatever to get the rock down there.
>> Typically we use a skid steer when we did the property and I believe it was 210
Lake Road last year.
We just use the skid steer to bring the
stone down to the site.
What little bit we used there, we didn't use a lot there to be honest, but and
there was not a significant, I mean there was considerable amount of traffic with heavy machinery going up and down the hill between the excavator and the skid steer.
And there was not really a significant amount of
soil erosion to the property.
And although the site
on
last year's project, the hill,
I would say is comparable
in pitch is to 85 Lake Road.
It's not as long.
It wasn't as long last year's project wasn't as long of a run.
But we didn't experience and we had some pretty heavy rains and like I mentioned on the sidewalk, we always keep bales of hay
on-site in case
we are predicting
any kind of heavy storms coming. We didn't really have any issues with
runoff into the water. The hill
on the last year's project was much closer to the lake than this one. There's there's a much more
flatter run out at 85
Lakeside.
So I don't really
foresee any issues with that. I was surprised
myself to see the
stone dust road that
the other company put in. I can't remember the name of the company now.
I've never seen anybody do that before,
to be quite honest.
>> Jeff, could you
perhaps mulch your hauler out?
I know that's one way of avoiding compaction or erosion
in those situations.
>> You could put mulch down, yep. Or just wood chips kind of thing. Yep.
In my opinion, I would be concerned about bringing a foreign wood chip material and have that run-in
to the lake, to be real honest with you. That was my actual thought with that stone dust driveway that the other company put in over at McGuire's property. I was a little surprised because,
I mean, that's an unwashed material
that they brought in from a sand and gravel pit. I mean, if we had that heavy rains and that were to wash into the lake,
I don't know what kind of impact that would have on the lake. That would be my concern only.
I know
last year John Valenti asked us to put wood chips behind the wall,
where we had seated.
He wanted to see wood chips there.
And, and that did wash into the lake during some heavy rains. So
I'm not sure if that's a viable option.
Like I said, we don't really,
we don't really have a lot of issues with the runoff. We've done two walls on the other side of like two years in a row.
Years we didn't have any issues with it at all.
>> This
isn't
a case where you wait until the ground is frozen necessarily.
>> The ground doesn't really freeze anymore.
So no, we don't. I would rather the ground be somewhat frozen except for obviously when we're excavating the,
you know, the lake area where we're going to build the wall, I'd rather it not be frozen solid.
As of right now, nothing's frozen. I don't see any cold weather in the near future.
So,
but again, like I said last year,
the last actually past previous years,
didn't experience any runoff whatsoever done into the lake.
Okay, thank you.
>> Any other
questions or comments
on the application?
Okay, I'm
certainly ready
to entertain
a motion.
You've got mail.
>> To approve
the
application
for
construction of the lake wall and fire pit at 85
Lakeside Drive, IWSWC
20 Dash 32.
>> Clarkson, I'll make a motion to approve application
20Dash32
for 85 Lakeside Drive.
I'll stop you, Matt.
>> Okay.
So I have a motion and a second.
Sorry, I was distracted by a couple of incomings.
I'll
go for a roll call.
Commissioner Hallisey?
Aye.
>> Commissioner Larson? Aye.
Commissioner Monroe?
Aye.
And Vice Chair Elliott,
also aye.
Motion carries four zero zero.
Again,
Regent Wagner will
communicate
decision two
week lag time, etcetera, standard conditions to apply.
But
you'll be good to go.
Now let's move on to the really vexing application,
February.
It doesn't look like we're going to be able to take action on this one tonight because
we don't have any new materials
And in particular, we don't have any indication of ALMA approval. I believe you said that, Jeff, that you'd have requested
it.
>> I did. I'm not really sure
Sorry. What happened
Somebody got to go shake the shake the branch as it were. I have to shake the tree one more time, I guess. Yes. And
I'm not overly concerned about that. That was not my primary application
that I was concerned with.
The 85 was my priority for now. So,
I'm assuming a job,
excuse me, a paid job. Yes, a paid job is more important than spending.
Home improvements.
>> So yeah, I guess I will have to,
contact Alcoa and find out what happened with that. I talked to Jeff Hayes, I believe it was Saturday.
He said he was emailing over his approval letter. I assumed
obviously wrongly that that implicated,
multiple letters,
letters, I guess is the word I was looking for. And he only approved the 85.
But like I said, I'm not
going to lose sleep over that.
>> Okay.
Truthfully, we could use
somewhat better detail in your plans and proposal
for that activity.
Sure, what would you Well,
>> again, better detail on the wall.
Discussed when
we had the sidewalk,
you showed us the
patio area, but we still don't have dimensions
areas So that would be
something that's closer to an actual site plan.
>> For both the wall and the patio? Yeah.
Okay. Yeah, the wall and the patio. Yeah, do realize I was somewhat vague because the whole thing was kind of like, well, let's get two permits while we're getting one. And I hadn't really put too much thought into the lake house. Honestly, it probably won't even get done this year, all right. Better site plans. Okay, I can do that.
Wall and patio.
Okay.
>> Anything else from commissioners?
Larsen, you already
commented on the hall route for the previous one, so I suppose that that question would also apply,
and the answer would be just about the same
if you're having to move I
>> would also make a follow-up
request that the homeowner consider
mitigation measures for the storm water that runs down into the lake there.
In the ideal world, that would include
gutters draining into a drywall kind of thing when you're putting the patio up.
Right. That'd be great.
>> Right. We did talk about that.
And,
yeah, we haven't solved that conundrum with the whole driveway.
I think we have probably more runoff coming off the driveway than I, than we do on the downspout drains. And I haven't quite
figured that out just yet.
But yes, we did talk about downspout drain,
dry wells and
and whatnot.
So I will
make note of that.
Okay, any other questions or concerns regarding the application?
If
>> not, I think, Jeff, we can let you go and proceed on to our next
agenda item.
Excellent, thank you.
>> Item number nine,
9A
and 9B
both being tightly linked enforcement actions.
Let's start with number 41.
We did receive some additional materials on that.
Agent Wagner, would you care to pick up the ball here and
describe
what you've seen?
Mindy, if you could bring up the photos that were posted online
regarding the remediation
at 41,
enforcement action at
Route 87.
And I see that the
owner is online and now visible.
Okay, here we go.
Now this is a
different set of photos. This regards
33.
The
photos,
and I'm sure I can't share my screen here.
>> Are they emailed to me, or are they on the website? They should be on the website.
>> Yeah, they uploaded.
It's labeled
41 Route 87,
photo submitted,
bone violation pictures, right?
They're under enforcement actions, not application.
That last one.
Okay, agent Wagner,
take it away. I
>> spoke to Kurt,
the property owner for 31 Route 87 last week.
They were in the process of doing
this work.
I haven't visited the site since it was late late last week that I talked to him.
He sent me these pictures.
This one's a view. Let's see. View of remediated section of 41 Route 87,
looking Southeast section of 33 Route 87 towards
41 Route 87 property. So you can see
41 Route 87 in the background there.
You can see the straw bales.
Then
they mentioned,
Kurt mentioned that they're going to put straw and grass seed down
to stabilize the area as much as the grass will grow in December.
Then they're
guy doing the site work painted a line to
demonstrate the areas that
where the where the film is removed.
This is a view from the opposite way looking towards Route 87
from the back of the area.
>> Okay, so we have some indication here that the
approved contractor
has
engaged in remediation
efforts
on
the
Route 87 side
of the water course.
Yes. But you haven't yet visited the site
to
verify
the scope of the work and
whether it's
essentially
adequate?
Not yet. Okay.
>> So at least
some progress
is being made.
Now you've represented
also that there would be no
that
activities on the other side of the
creek at the 33
Route 87 side
would not
commence until
the work at 41
was completed,
and they have to move the shed.
>> Yeah. That no. The appeal
window for the permit just, that just expired on Saturday.
So
they didn't they started the forty one
first. That was the priority according to Kurt.
>> Okay. And, again, you haven't visited to ascertain if anything has been done
subsequent to that communication?
I have not. Okay.
>> Now, on the other side of the creek, we have
some communication
from the property owner and
a couple of photographs. I don't know if those have been posted or is there or no,
Mindy, you have those, right?
In the email, the photographs you started to show of views of 33
Route 87
from 41. Right, okay.
Now, I
can't interpret
these photographs,
but
I believe the
photographer
the landowner is on
the call. So
Ms. Nichols, if you could
explain what you're trying to convey here.
>> Hello, miss Nichols, can you unmute? I'm sorry that I was muted. So
the corner that
you could see, that's the flat area.
That was the work that Mark Williams has been excavating.
And the view that you are seeing with all those rocks,
that's the part that's on the other side of the hay bales that you don't see.
And this deposition
was
done,
as you can see, in December
2019.
And one year later,
it is still there.
And that was needed to be put there so the
shed that was not permitted can be platformed.
And those boulders are still there. And I just wanted to make sure that that is going to be part of the remediation.
When I spoke to Mark Williams,
he told me that he was focusing
on
the land that was closer to the stakes. And that's what you saw that he did work on. That's why it's all flat and gradient.
But he was not going to do anything with
the bank of the stream
because that's not what he was contracted to do.
So that is when I took the view of
these rocks and boulders
because he gave me the impression that this was something
that he was not even going to touch. And that's clearly in the wetlands area.
And
I know that you said that the priority was 41 Route 87.
>> No, not priority,
but simply the first order of business.
>> Okay, because the violation has been since February.
And now, all of a sudden, December 1, it seems like it's a priority.
So I just wanted to
make sure,
because of what he did for the shed,
that's where all these boulders are. And that's
not even the first thing that he's working on. He's working on clearing his land and making that flat rather than working with the area that could potentially directly affect the brook, the wetland area,
which is obviously my concern with my house being
down a hill that empties into a brook that could potentially be dammed.
I just don't know how much longer
this needs to go on,
where we just wait for Kurt's
our priority and an enforcement action.
I've been to seven different every month I come to this meeting and something is always
prolonged because it's not
Mr. Boham's agenda or priority
and we just doing whatever he wants to do on his agenda rather than anybody else's and it's just very very frustrating
as I state in every meeting and I'm hoping that it gets recorded in the minutes
each time that we
look for progress. And it's only when it's convenient for Mr. Bohum, not when it's convenient for the other people that it's affecting.
>> Take your point.
And
again, without having a direct familiarity
with the work that has been done.
I can
only refer this to Adrian Wagner to follow-up. And again, as we said at our last meeting, we really do
action on this,
but the commission does
not enforce.
The commission
rules.
We
can only work through
our agent
to get things
done.
And I know that
agent Wagner has been active and tried to communicate
And Mr.
If Mr. Boehm
isn't
following up,
the only thing we can do as a next step would
be to try to,
well, we would basically have to take it to court.
>> Well, we've been saying this, I mean, in September,
mean, I hopefully recorded the minutes, of you stated if that shed is not moved, I don't care if he moves it to his front yard, we will take action, we will take action. I continue to hear the same thing.
Agent Wagner stated, he talked to Mr. Boheme. He said, this
is what he's doing. We've been talking to Mr. Boheme since September.
It's now December 1,
and now we are just starting to take action.
And again,
it's just a recycled
saying that I'm just hearing over and over again the same thing. We could only do so much. Well, it seems Mr. Bohum could do whatever he wants.
So we're at the point where we're going to do what we want to our side of the book because it doesn't matter. The commission is not going to do anything.
That's basically the I
>> don't that attitude if I were you. I think it would be ill advised
to
take matters into your own hands here.
Just my frustration is The point is, yes, I realize it's going very slowly.
And
that
there have been a number of delaying
factors
such as getting approval for the contractor.
I mean, that was a big hitch for a long time there. And then contractor got approved and the contractor was ready to do the work and seems that he started the work. But again,
based on the information
we have present and the information you provided,
obviously,
he hasn't done but half a job.
And a lot more is going to be required,
including moving the shed.
I don't mean to cut Because the shed has got to be relocated. I know what's going be done on I the
>> don't mean to cut you off, but I know what needs to be done. I know what's been done. It's just very frustrating when
I come to meetings. I've come to 12 meetings,
12 meetings,
and we're still having these meetings about it.
I have a contractor's information since August.
He started December 1.
So
my time is valuable, just like I appreciate your time is valuable. But twelve months on the same issue,
we all know what the issue is,
but we also know who is dictating when it's going to be done.
So I don't understand where the enforcement is.
>> Again, appreciate your concern.
And
I think we will continue to try and get things moving.
But as I said,
the commission per se
cannot enforce.
And frankly,
the regulations are such
that
the process is slow.
Will
>> So how do I contact your lawyer or attorney to You don't. The next level? You don't.
Well, then
why would I want to come to a meeting
and even have this on your agenda if nothing is To provide information
>> about what's happening.
Because absent that, we don't even know
that there's still an issue. We get some follow-up,
but you
were the one who initiated
the action in the first place. Right. And we're relying on you in part and your role here.
>> So
would you like a weekly update every Monday? Should I give an update? No, because we won't be able to receive it.
I'll send it over an email. I
>> can send You it up in two can certainly be in contact with Agent Wagner.
>> And I do hear I appreciate you sends me the email for the agenda, and I respond with concerns. But I
don't feel my
concerns are being addressed. They're just
being appeased by putting me on the agenda.
I mean, if you look, I have all the agendas printed. I have twelve months of agendas with my name on it.
Twelve months of That's right. It's a continuing problem.
>> Well, then how do we rectify this? We just wait for somebody else to be convenient for them?
And I hope that my basement doesn't flood or my front yard doesn't flood and then I have issues?
I just have to cross my fingers and hope that Mother Nature is going to be good to us.
>> And we, the commission,
have to continue
to try to get Mr. Bohm to act. We do that, as I said, thirst by our agent and feeling that
we have to initiate legal action. Trust me, will not be fast either.
>> Right. In my January minutes
sorry, my July minutes, it says that you would be contacting your attorney to look into legal action.
That was the July minutes.
It is now December.
So
should I be the one asking for the attorney follow-up? What is the action that you are now taking?
This was in the minutes that you guys have posted that you would be contacting the attorney for legal action.
So
how do I
>> don't believe that we said that we would. We said we might consider,
and that's a different matter. We said failing
action.
And in any event
I'll have to Legal action would
be a matter of last resort.
You won't get anything,
nothing will happen quickly
if it has to go to court, especially
under present conditions
where court actions are curtailed.
Concern is that COVID restrictions.
Understand your concern. You're worried about flooding.
And
that's a valid concern.
Our concern is how to get this done and how to light a fire under Mr. Boehm to make it happen.
And
again,
I'm
going to have to refer to Agent Wagner
as the point person
for that.
And I
hope that the commission is in agreement
that this should probably take highest
priority
in his
activities.
We know what needs to be done.
The plan for remediation
and the approved
relocation of the shed
are all there.
So
it
seems to me
simply a matter of getting
that work to be done.
Given that we know what needs to be done,
how do we
get
Mr. Bohm to
follow
on those
requirements?
>> This has been since February. He knew what needed to be done, and you've been asking him to follow.
That's just
>> Well, that's not entirely true because there was the whole shed issue, and the shed had to be moved
before
anything
could be before the fill on his side of the creek could be
addressed.
And the permit for the shed was first denied and then approved.
Delays, structural delays, systemic delays
occurred.
And
well, that may be aggravating.
>> It's also Well, due respect to Commissioner
Elliott, I mean, I don't want to you guys have been on for two and a half hours. We don't need to rehash. We all know what's been going on. I just wanted to be
listening to what
the commission was doing about it. So you don't have to rehash the timeline. I know that. We all know that. We are all part of this. So whatever you need to do to move on.
>> Vice Chairman Elliott, I do have a question.
Yeah.
At the last meeting, we discussed the fact that we would be getting a
remediation
plan.
And
I see we have not got one of those. Do we have a due date
by which we expect to get the plan from Mr. Bohm?
>> I can't answer that question immediately because I've got to refer to
the documents.
Let's see now.
>> I know I didn't see anything new online
on a remediation plan. And so
my suspicion is that we probably have not given him a deadline
to present the plan.
And
we need to do that so that we can be ready to take legal action.
>> On your August 3 minute,
it states,
George Eliot said the commission can construct a timeline
in terms of the legal requirement of what the commission
needs to do for the next steps.
And they would
contacting the attorney if they don't get any action.
And that was on the August 3
meeting.
That I know was speaking to the timeline of action, But again, that was discussed back in August
about
steps not being followed and what is the timeline for that.
>> Yeah, that was in response to a letter from your attorney about effectuating the order. And I think that that
was sidelined by the
SHED application
and the discussion stating that
you had given permission
for the contractor
to access the property. That's what I'm seeing from the last minute. Right. That was It on the seemed at that point that things were beginning to move forward.
And obviously,
they moved very, very little.
I mean,
the forward motion
is simply
it's moving, but it isn't moving very much is the problem.
The job has been started,
but
it doesn't seem to show any signs of current you're saying there hasn't been any current progress.
And
the issue now is to, you know,
how can we get Mr. Boehm to get the job finished?
>> So
when I go back and then look at the September
meeting
when you were asking for
information
for a permit application
for the shed as well as
to
remove all the deposition material from that area in the slope.
That's when Agent Wagner recommended
Mr. Bohum to follow the plan
and remove the material concurrently with the file permit
modification.
And
agent Wagner confirmed that no action at that time was taken or to remediate.
agent Wagner said that attorney Mark Bram was informed.
And the next step would be for the town to take legal action through the state Supreme Court.
They corrected
Wagner to contact Attorney Brantz if no progress was made and draft a motion for the next step discussed at the October meeting.
However, at that October meeting,
there was not this discussion. So it was noted in your September minutes
that this is what the steps should be,
but that was not followed up in the October meeting.
>> Again, I'll simply state that it seemed that progress was being made
without recourse to
legal action,
and that
it now appears that such action
is
proceeding simply by fits and starts,
and that
we need to
goad
Mr. Bohm into
finishing the work that's been started.
>> And then on your October meeting,
again, you said the next step of the commission would be communicate with your attorney regarding injunctions, fines, and superior court. And Agent Wagner should communicate again the next step and the importance with Mr. Bohum.
So again, there's three months in a row where you are stating that there should be some going forward
with
information,
talking to your attorney and some legal action.
And then
unfortunately, I wasn't able to
go to the
November meeting,
and there seems to be no discussion.
When I wasn't present at that meeting,
There's nothing
listed in the
sorry, I take that back.
>> We did actually discuss that. And that was when we came up that
I just I'm sorry. I lost the minutes there. Yeah. I found them. Yep.
And it looked
>> Our
minutes
from the
November 2 meeting
do indicate that we had continued discussion.
>> Yeah. Basically,
it also states
just suggestion
on where the shed could be moved.
Again, But it's talking about still waiting to receive the permit.
And
the cease and correct order should be enforced independently
of the shed.
So again, now this is three
months prior. We were talking about following up with legal action.
Then we had something a little bit. Now the SHED application has expired, and there's still no change.
>> Let
me ask Agent Wagner here about the situation with the SHED. We basically
turned that over to the shed application because it was an upland reviewer.
>> The permit was issued to relocate the shed 10 feet.
There was a fifteen day
appeals period.
I should
forget what day. Was like mid November that I issued the permit.
But anyway, the appeal period just expired Saturday.
So
that would be a
I advised Kurt that it was probably best to wait till the peer the appeal period was over before
this did anything with the shed.
And they were, you know, at the time I was talking to them, were in the course of working on 41
Route 87 anyway.
So I kinda lined up time wise that
they could start working on the shed. And I said, I haven't been there. I haven't talked to him since then. So I don't know what's happened.
That was Thursday.
Nothing.
>> Did we not have a remediation plan before we actually execute
the non plan?
>> We had engineering recommendations
for remediation
that included
removal of debris,
installation of geo fabric, and rip rack.
All that has
been communicated
early on in the process.
>> So it seemed to be sufficient. We as a commission didn't
act on that to say whether or not that was sufficient. That was by the same engineer that recommended
moving the shed four feet.
>> That was my follow-up question.
That's Andrew Bushnell,
the civil engineer. There were seven recommendations that he gave
when I talked to Mark Williams.
I want to say he was only going to do four of those. There was nothing that had to do with the
grading of the slope
and that he was basically just removing
and putting the bales of hay. So that's why I also wanted to follow-up to make sure that
I would guess
either Agent Wagner or Andrew Bushnell be the one to go and sign off that it was done back to its original?
Again, my bigger concern and you saw that pile of rocks is that
because of gravity, they're going to fall into the stream, and it's going to dam it all up.
I think they're at their angle of repose.
>> Any event Well, they weren't there originally, and they're on my property. So I guess then I will have to do a trespass thing or something.
>> That's what I'm just trying to figure out. Yeah. But it sounds like, from your communication, the contractor may be misinformed
as to what's really required here.
>> And that's, I think, what I wanted to make sure that was communicated
through Agent Wagner is,
like Commissioner Larson was saying, we have this remediation process.
But
that doesn't mean that
that's what's communicated to somebody who's actually commissioned to do the work.
Right.
So that was something I also wanted to make sure. We have this plan in place.
And is it being filed, is it just somebody else's interpretation of what needs to be done to satisfy the commission when, again,
yes, it's the wetlands. Yes, it's my property. So if I have to do something from my end for my property,
that's what I need to do. But I was really hopeful that the town was going to do that because it is in the wetlands area.
>> Okay.
Jed,
you raised the point about remediation
plan.
All we have
that I can find is the original order to remediate,
which the
final,
penultimate
paragraph,
the order
states that they have to be remediated within 100 feet.
I believe that let's see now. Where are the
recommendations
from
I have those.
>> Engineer Bushnell.
Was that included in the permit application
for the shed,
the permit application that we denied?
I think you were treating them separately.
But they were linked.
Again, we could
>> Yeah, the seven points that I have from Andrew Bushnell
is that the shed
should be relocated
six feet north.
The field was going to be removed and relocated
closer
to
away from the stream in a level area. Hay bales will be installed for erosion control,
removal of any visible debris or large stones from the embankment.
And then this geotextile
should be installed
along with a layer
of riprap rock over the geotextile
and then loom, seed, and mulch. Those are the seven recommendations.
Right.
And
>> And it's my understanding that
Mr. Williams was
communicated about the hay bales,
removing
stuff that was on our property line, but he didn't even go near the
embankment in there.
>> Okay.
So,
Agent Wagner, do you have
the
recommendations
from
engineer Bushnell
regarding remediation,
especially as regards to
the
removal
of materials
following
the relocation of the shed.
Well, they're they were incorporated into
the application.
>> Yeah. That's what I thought. And so
but
since since the original application, you know, those carried forward? Sorry.
My recollection didn't serve. Were those recommendations carried forward into the
reapplication?
>> Yeah, the geotextile,
the riprap, the removal and fill,
then relocation of the shed has changed from six feet to 10 feet. Okay, So we so getting back to commissioner Larson's
>> question. Yeah. There is
a sufficient plan
for remediation.
Again, the sticking point is
to
get Mr. Bone
and his contractor
to get the work done.
And since the work has started,
it's
a matter of
making, you know, getting some progress and getting some progress
that's not just in fits and starts
and not just dependent on,
well, my contractor
wants to schedule at some other time or,
you know,
and I don't know, again,
legal action,
although perhaps the threat of legal action might speed things up, legal action per se
isn't going to make it happen any faster.
>> They will prove a point to him that it's not on his budget when it's convenient for him.
>> I think that's what we have to communicate. As I say,
the legal action would simply defer
any action, any activity
until
it goes through the courts.
Well, I like that think we'd rather Commissioner would rather see it gets get done sooner.
>> Talking about a timeline. There's no timeline. It's basically
whenever it's convenient, so I like Commissioner
Larson's suggestion of having a timeline.
>> Can
we agree that it perhaps.
The agent agent.
I agree
with her discuss the
parameters of work, the
extent of what work is actually required.
That seems to be the big issue right here. I mean, there's equipment on-site,
pay bills are there.
I have no idea what the contractor schedule is.
It seems to be moving forward. Problem that as I see it is, seems
to be,
the
extent of work isn't clear.
>> It might be clear. It just, I don't know what the timeline is. And like I said, they're working on one particular area,
and that's not even the area
to me that's near the wetland that is going to, the slope and all that stuff. I get it. He's clearing that area. It's off my property. But what about the other part of the property where the actual brook is?
I would have thought that would have been the first priority, getting the deposition away from the brook.
And when I talked to Mark Williams, he
wasn't under the impression that he was going to have to do the slope or anything like that. So that's why
I was like, well, wait a second. Yeah, it's nice that you're to get it off of my property, but my bigger concern is the brook. What's gonna happen to the brook?
>> So I guess there just needs to be some clarification as to what
is responsible for.
>> Right. And I think that is covered
in the remediation
plan.
And
agent Wagner pointed out in the application
to
essentially relocate the shed
prior to the
removal
and remediation
activities.
But it does seem that
the contractor
may not be
fully informed of the scope of work.
And so I guess that at this point we should,
as you say, have
agent Wagner communicate
those requirements,
and
it would be up to us
to
determine
if we want to,
what would be an appropriate
timeline
for completing this activity.
Frankly, I have no idea
what would be,
you know, what kind of work
is required or how much time it will take to get the work done.
And we're not really certain right now as
to how much of the work has been done, although it seems like it's very little.
Major Wagner, could you weigh in on this
and give us a sense of when you can
what you can see as a potential
for
getting this done?
And as a plan and
what it will take?
>> I'm not yeah. I'm not really sure what your question is.
>> What is it gonna take to get this done in your opinion?
>> Well, the
I mean, just doing it. The paperwork's in place. The permit is in place. The appeal period is passed. So
that should
all the
wetlands red tape is out of the way. So now it's up to Curt and the contractor to just do it.
>> Okay.
And can
you communicate a sense of urgency
to Mr. Vaughn
about getting this work done?
Yeah. And
>> maybe
raise the stick
of what it would be entailed for
enforcement action.
If we have to take it to the next step,
what's going to come down on him?
>> Can I ask you
one question based on a picture that I sent?
Is the one that you saw with all the
boulders,
are those going to be removed?
>> That was my understanding that any material that was put in there as fill
will have to be removed. I
>> just want to make sure that I was clearly understanding because,
again, that was put there to make space for that platform.
All right. Gentlemen, I am sorry that I have to take so much of your time. And I do appreciate
what you're trying to do. So thank you again.
And I will
see you, I guess, for the
January meeting. Is that the next one? Our next meeting will be in January.
But feel free to contact any time.
Oh, I will. Thank you again. Okay.
>> So
I return to the regulations.
It's not really clear,
exactly
what would occur
if we have to take legal action.
But
I think we can
be assured
that
it would not be favorable
for Mr. Baldwin.
I just want it to get done. And
>> don't as I say, I think that that would really constitute
a delay of the game.
But
at the same time,
if
the work is ready to be done, and
Agent as Wagner says, everything seems to be in place for it to be done,
then
I don't know what else we can do
to
get it completed.
I'd be happy to entertain any suggestions from the Commission.
Okay.
Well,
I guess that
the
commission right now
should simply
continue.
And
I don't know.
I'm not sure that I understand what sequence
is now.
Agent Wagner, you mentioned something that had expired. Which what had expired now?
>> The appeals period for a public
to appeal agent just an agent's decision
to issue the permit.
>> Oh, okay. Right. I got you. I got you. The the two week.
Yeah. Okay. So he can now
He can act on the permit. He can act on the permit. Yeah. Okay.
So I guess that, we'd like you to communicate with him about
actually going ahead and
moving on the permit. Yeah. Okay.
>> Well, this is the this I mean,
I feel like it should have been done earlier, but it's like every all the steps are now, like, it's got a permit to relocate a shed.
He's got permission to access the land.
Right. Like, everything's out of the way for the project to get completed. So the next step would be legal action because that's the only thing left. Right.
But And that's where that's where we're what we've been working towards. And now that if if nothing gets done, then legal action is the next practical thing because we have a trail of we we issued a permit. We've come up with a remediation plan.
>> Right.
Permission. And especially
now that the permit
appeals
has expired.
>> Yeah. Already no Yeah. Place to do it. So now it's on him to do it. And if he doesn't do it, then we can do legal action knowing that we've done every step previous to
>> Right. Okay.
So
we've had,
what,
about two weeks
since the
>> appeal period expired. Right? No. It's it expired Saturday.
So Oh, just the Saturday. Okay. Yeah. It's been
two days.
Okay.
So
there's still a little window.
>> Yeah.
It's just because the whole process took so long. I mean, it's it's kinda like we should've hit we should've got this point
probably in the summer, but with the turnover with agents and everything, it it just didn't happen, I guess. Yeah. And again, the denial
>> of the first permit request
kind of threw a wrench into the
progress and into the process.
He really couldn't
do anything without
moving the ship. Correction, yeah. Yeah,
yeah. Okay,
>> so Would it be fair
to
say that it should be complete by the time we get together a month from now?
I would like to see at least substantial progress.
>> Can we On on day have agent Wagner ask
Kurt Bohm when he's gonna be done?
>> I can do that. I can ask him for a date.
I was under the impression talking to him that he wanted to get it done
as quickly as we want him to get it done.
I'm not sure if that's true or not, but that's what he told me. So
>> Well, again, if he has the permission to move the shed and
can then subsequently
remove the fill and remediate the
disturbance,
then there's no reason for him not to go ahead.
And I think it would be correct for you to ask him for,
okay, when are you going to get this done? Give me a date. And communicate that to us
so that
we can determine whether it's a reasonable
deal
and not, well, do it when I get around to it
kind of response.
We need a hard deadline.
And
again, communicate that failing that,
we're going to have to take legal action.
So if you can communicate that
and
get it back to the commission,
I think that that would
resolve
well, that's as much as we can do right now.
Yeah.
>> But I do think we need to make a priority having it complete.
And we're already late because
we
wanted this complete before we got
done with the drought
so that if we do get a lot of rain and it starts washing through there, it doesn't wash those boulders down to block the creek.
>> We're living on Bora Of 9 suspect that those boulders are at their angle of repose.
And it would take
a hellacious flood
to move
those objects. But still in all, yeah, it's getting wet. And it's not going to be any easier to get the work done.
So
I
agree with you, Commissioner Lawson, that we would like to see this done
by our next meeting.
Next time we have to talk about it, I want to hear a report that says
it's finished.
We can
have done with that cease and desorce order.
Okay, anything else on the issue?
Are we clear where we need to go?
Major Wagner, any questions?
No. Okay.
Then
I would like to move on to the agent report, which I suspect we have already heard most Thank you. I
>> don't have anything other
than what we've already talked about.
>> Joe, have you have you seen the temporary road that's been put on in on 422
Lake Road?
>> No. I talked to I think it was
Jim Blair.
I went and visited the site with him before they started the work,
but I haven't seen it since it started.
>> I would think that the I was surprised at the material that he put in there
and with the heavy rains that we have had recently.
I can't tell from walking down the road how much he's run down the hill into the lake from that. But
sedimentation
of the lake being the concern that it is,
I would think that that road would have aggravated that as opposed to helping it.
>> Jed, do you recall the application number for that?
You're
talking about the
stonewall at the
other side of the lake from where we're looking, what was that? I do not have the application number, but I do recall
>> doing the site visit
there,
there was no discussion of
a temporary road or anything like that? Yeah,
>> would call that a haul route.
But nevertheless,
the fact is if it wasn't in
the application,
I think we do have an issue.
I'm just trying to find out.
Okay, that's application number 20.
At a quick glance, I don't see any mention
of
putting in a hauler out or
stone dust hauler out
for moving materials for that construction.
Now they talk about using the excavator. They talk about
measures for erosion control and so forth, but again, nothing about that.
>> It could be that he has silt fence down there that's stopping any of that material from getting in the water. I was just very surprised
at the extensive nature of
whatever you called it. To me, it was just a temporary road to all the stone
back down
that way.
>> Yeah, exactly.
And again, the purpose of that
stone dust is to
prevent compaction and
tearing up the ground
while you're doing it. But I think
perhaps we could ask Agent Wagner to
check-in on that, see what
the skinny is
in terms of,
again, avoiding impact
from that material.
Are
there controls in place to avoid erosion?
What's the long term
plan
for that haul route?
>> Yeah, I think when I talked to him, they were going to
remove it when they were done. I remember him talking about putting gravel down.
Okay.
And then he was putting a soap fence,
you know,
on the water side, and then he was
put tarps down
to do the work. And then when they're done at the end of the night, they would fold the tarps back up Mhmm. To cover the wall as it was under construction.
Right. Right.
K.
>> So it should be
there's, two the tarps and the the silt fence
will both prevent any of that from getting into the water. It should. Okay. So But I can take a ride down there and and take a look at it.
>> Yeah. I'm not saying he's doing anything wrong. I know he's got a great reputation for doing doing good work. It just surprised me with the type of material that was being hauled in there to create this road that I said,
I was just surprised because we had no discussion of it.
>> Yeah, as you say, especially since it wasn't mentioned
in the
in the application.
Okay. Well, any other
business?
K.
Hearing none,
our next regular meeting will be in 2021
on January 4 at 7PM
on the usual
well, on your usual device, I guess I could say, rather than usual place.
And with
that,
I would be happy to entertain a motion for adjournment.
I move we adjourn.
Second to that motion?
>> Looks like we lost Bill.
It's up to you, Jim.
>> Okay. Jim's muted, but I can tell by his lips that he's saying yes.
So I will now
ask for a vote on that non debatable motion.
Commissioner Hallisey,
raise your hand if you are in favor of adjourning.
Commissioner Larson,
same sign.
And I also vote to adjourn. The meeting is adjourned at 10:15PM.
Thank you all. Thank you, Mindy, for hanging in there with us.
And
again, we'll be in touch with
communications,
about the enforcement
action and so forth,
between now and the next meeting. And we'll see you all
on
Saturday
morning
beginning Thanks, Joe.
>> Okay.
Good night, all.
Good night. Good night. Now click on leave meeting.